i've got something joe
whenever mark's done
sorry yeah my internet's a bit iffy so
sorry mark can you say it again
sure so um i i think i know
you're going with this but but can you
tell me how you
arrived at that conclusion because i'm
not sure you're wrong
so i'm just trying to figure out what
what led you there
so first
i thought okay so with
me the traditional meta you're just sort
of
you know you're radiating compassion
towards people
so it seemed like you were actively
trying to
cultivate the perspective of a
compassionate person and thereby
the virtue of compassion and so
but then john john's idea
of meta seems to be like
that that's sort of like a indirect way
of
cultivating something else which is
understanding that your your
co-identifications
like with others are not
like fixed and you there's always
more to people and it appears
and then like recently i've looked into
what exactly he meant by reverence
and that basically is what reverend says
it seems to be that
you're because obviously all it's about
um
relating properly to all which is like
it's got something to do with curiosity
going beyond
you know the the common like your own
understanding of things just remaining
aware
that you the reality
always exceeds you and it's always
drawing you beyond
you know your your conceptions and so if
meta is about
trying to remind yourself that the way
you're co-identifying
you know isn't all there is
and therefore to create more
i'd call it participatory flexibility
then it seems like you are basically
cultivating
reverence
okay so i and i'd love to hear what ben
has to say about this but my
understanding of meta is that it was
always doing those things we're always
supposed to
and maybe john's emphasis is a little
bit different but i would say that
reverence is an emergence from
meta with moreness and suchness or
something
as the as the additional focus so
a lot of the ecologies overlap and
there's a perspectival overlap here with
others
everything everything has a perspectival
aspect which i think is primary actually
for lots of reasons i don't think john
would disagree with that
and then there's a bunch of stuff that's
participatory to your point
about reciprocal opening
and that's the moreness versus the
suchness so the
suchness is the grounding and the
moreness is the opening to new
potential or possibility and then the
reason why he does that
is to is to do that opponent processing
did you stop talking or if i lost
connection
i think you okay
so sorry what what was the main thrust
of that
because it sounded just like a yes
basically
and yeah i'm curious to hear what ben
thinks
[Music]
so
well velocity what i was going to ask
you if that
if your sense of this is consistent with
your practice of meta
or how that's showing up for you in your
life it's just it's sort of a
baby idea like i'm not i've been doing
meta the whole may you'd be happy
well and free of suffering so far
and so i've been thinking about changing
to the morning suchness thing and so
but but it also it sort of seemed a bit
like uh
so i was just playing around with the
whole maybe it is literally just the
cultivation of reverence and then that
would
connect to me so i'm wondering do you
have a sense of awe
at times in your life that you can
recollect
i would say okay
and do you have a sense of whether or
not you're
relating to those in a way that you
would deem to be reverent
i'm not sure okay because then we can we
could check phenomenologically
experientially does
meta seem to relate to that right maybe
[Music]
do i jump in
always count
um i get where you're going i think
veloskin and i like it too
because i think the direction of what
you're talking about is like a
reverential attitude towards other
people
correct me if i'm wrong
yeah yeah and although i think john has
said that you can you can actually
perform better on
non-human things
right yeah
i like i like that
in terms of i suppose recognizing the
sacred in other people
and to by extension recognizing the
sacred in the world
that's that's good that needs to be done
reverently
um so not to take anything away from
that but to try and make something a
little bit more
um current i think the last
time i heard him talk about it john that
is
was in the cultivating wisdom stoicism
peace did you catch that one
could you give me a bit more english
you know how nowadays he's doing instead
of like a daily sit with everybody in
the sangha he's doing like a saturday
teaching no i haven't caught up to it
yet
i'll just inject this as another thread
rather than as any kind of
yes or no he put meta
in the context of the
confusion between having mode and being
mode
as i say this isn't to say yes or no to
where you're going with it but
just to put a new thread maybe it won't
go anywhere
so using meta as a
psychotechnology to what did he say
better contemplation is the way to fix
the confusion
that seems to fit because i've thought
of the having mode
as being a rigidity
of perspectival and participatory
knowing it's where you
kind of assume it then you leave it
static and then you get on
and then you a little bit more
so creative with your proposition on
your
um procedure on
like you assume it's sort of like you're
assuming that what you value
and the way that you're looking at
things is right
you don't really reflect him anymore and
you're just
achieving the goal whereas i i sort of
think as the being knows the
opposite
yeah i think i think all that's correct
uh airports are loud by the way so
sorry about that um i think
regular meta does this right but what
john does is add in the concept of the
opponent processing with the moreness
and the suchness and detach the rooting
versus the
expansion so you see this for example in
the practice the the seated moving
practice
and then the chakra expansion lesson
that he does in meditation
so he kind of emphasizes this idea of
going from rooted
to expanding and that's not only
opponent processing but it's also the
flexibility and it's also
opening you up for the possibility of
reverence so i don't think they're
training revenge
but opening the possibility
um also earlier there was discussion of
the word
curiosity and uh
a word adjacent to that that's been
interesting in similar conversations is
wonder
as the like curiosity is the
seeking of the next proposition whereas
wonder is like
the participatory analogy of that of
like
seeking how the mystery will unfold next
so that might be useful language
you might have to come again there
jarvis i didn't hear any of that
oh i'm sorry um
how do i send now
that came through okay um
it's just the word wonder which um
like when making the distinction between
like taking the participatory to be
fixed
and seeking more in the propositional
i've heard that be described as
curiosity in contrast to wonder
which is seeking more in the unfolding
again i don't know sorry sorry i think
i think that's you jules not because i
i'm hearing in the pie come on
oh i can't i'll drop out and come back
oh gosh
um yeah well i guess i got my point
across
is that all good yeah
that sounds right to me
yeah i it's sort of
maybe i'm getting a bit too often a
tangent
the i've been thinking there's sort of a
this idea that maybe there is a
virtue there's like two versions of
each virtue there's one
that sort of
maybe we could say epistemic and then
there's one that's
ethical so you might say curiosity you
know
the pair of curiosity and wonder the
sort of doing the same thing but
curiosity is more about gaining
propositions and procedures i suppose
and the others about gaining
perspectives and
participatory performances
and then maybe you could replicate that
to
other things like uh
i wouldn't know what word to use but
like
doubt and something
to go along with curiosity
confusion
i'd be interested where humility fits
into that as well
that might be it
no no no it's definitely very relevant
though
because to it
like the what the wonder promotes
humility
because it's it's a recognition that you
are insufficient
that you're not complete
but that that goes both for
i don't there is more that i can
should we say gain but it also goes for
maybe what i've got now
is wrong
i also like thinking about it in terms
of humility
because experientially when i experience
curiosity it's it's kind of from a uh
egotistic proud standpoint of oh let me
examine this and so i can control it and
understand it whereas
the wonders and maybe this is where
reverence comes into
is the stronger sense of humility and
respect
that comes from that
yeah i don't think you can directly
train wonder
or reverence i think they're
second-order effects
right and then the way you engender them
is
by increasing your perspectival
flexibility
and uh focusing
on opening up right and the opening up
will take care of the humility
automatically
so this is just one of those overlapping
things because this theme is elsewhere
in john's ecology
and he talks about it in the meditation
series so
the prajna is very much like this too
where you're like
you know when you get to prajna it's
like whoa what are you actually doing
here i mean i don't i can't even do the
prajna
but but i don't think there's anything
like i said in the in the
current meditation tradition that meta
doesn't already enable that
i think that john may be emphasizing it
more but
like i i don't ben would be the only one
that could answer something like that if
some of the traditions
maybe emphasize the whole humility and
reverence side of things
but but but it's not a direct effect
right it's more like if you're lucky
you'll get reverence
if you do this maybe you know that that
sort of thing
i think i can kind of see your point
about it it's hard to teach someone
humility but i think i
want to push back a little bit on the
idea that you can't try to cultivate it
maybe after the fact after you've
experienced it and
i've come to value humility and
reverence
and wonder that you can't
try to cultivate that i think i've had
mixed success in my
attempts personally yeah
actually i think i was saying the
opposite i like the word cultivate i
like how you picked up on that yeah
right so you're putting forth a field
with the appropriate seeds and
soil and water cultivate reverence
that doesn't mean that you're gonna get
it right it just means that you're more
likely to get it if you invite it in
or if you invite these other uh things
in that are close to reverence
and that i think is is is what john's
going after
i think john's very humble in what this
can what can be achieved
etc but but meta i've i've always seen
that as
engendering the sorts of things that
will increase all wonder and reverence
over
time anyway and it really is just a
difference between a duck for john he's
just emphasizing that one piece
and he does he does this with vipassana
and mindfulness too right he changes
them just slightly
or focuses them in a different way than
say from normal
uh because he's after a very specific
goal but but i think those things are
all the things he's trying to cultivate
are things like that right i think his
main thrust is to cultivate virtue or
something
right or things that are like virtues
yeah this this reminds me of something
actually so
the way so you know how
it's often said that the
academics like the more you know the
more you know
you don't know or whatever
i think like that that comes from the
fact that each time you learn
something you're witnessing directly
the insufficiency of your own
you know knowledge set or whatever and
so
i can see why like i'm connecting this
to how you say
you can't like deliberately like teach
or get
wonder but you have to cultivate it
by repeatedly like going going through
some level of transformation in the
first place
so you can directly witness you know
you're directly witnessing how there is
more
to reality you're seeing
how you can go beyond rather than being
told
for some reason when you're talking
velocity there's a
verse in proverbs which is coming to my
mind which is
the fear of the lord is the beginning of
wisdom
that's not to be evangelical but rather
to point to what you're talking about
which is
first having a transformative experience
leads you into that wonder and
recognition of your own
relative ignorance compared to the ocean
of
wisdom if you're looking in that right
lens in that transformed
lens
i also feel the cultivation
uh versus directly seeking
lines up with the modal confusion um
that rather than try to have wonder you
try to
have perhaps you try to
be um open or
be a field that can support a crop
so that one's up for me
yeah i feel like a lot of this goes back
to my thesis about meditation being
about second order effects
right and if that's true then what
you're doing is cultivating the field
and hoping that
something germinates or something like
that and in
in which case for anything you think
that might be the case i agree
but if you're going to make the
statement that if you meditate you'll
get x
then i'm going to disagree uh you know
for for most things
like like about the only thing
meditation can give you directly that
you can measure is something like a
slower heart rate
and even that's not 100 so
yeah there are still issues like your
oxygenation levels go up your heart rate
modulate we'll say uh there's a couple
of other things
uh your brainwave state changes right
and and then that engenders a long
lasting effect
uh uh across the three axes we'll say
but
other than that it's you know it's not
clear to me
uh uh what else it would give you that's
a that's a first order effect we'll say
i really like the old the design thing i
always heard
which is um enlightenment is an accident
meditation makes you accident praying
oh i love that i'm all in yeah i like
the word cultivate i think we should
adopt that i think that was a really uh
i think that was a really salient use of
the term in in just the right way
right because cultivation doesn't mean
success right it just means you're
setting up the conditions
and and i think that's really where it's
at i think that's what john's going for
ultimately
feel free to add to this one
or change the subject
going back to what ben said velocin
the phenomenology of it what led you to
that
is cultivating reverence
[Music]
i don't know if i could explain anymore
about what led me to the
notion
maybe you won't hear what i said it was
just basically uh
so i've been on this idea of
contemplations
where we are trying to
cultivate virtues specifically
so i had this
so like i i had this idea of
let's take three virtues i had what i
call compassion which is
you know seeing others as valuable like
yourself
uh prudence just seeing your future self
like your present self
and uh and then en
encretia which is just general sort of
not being immediate impression
so the idea would be that say with
compassion
you you put yourself in the
you're sitting down specifically to
contemplate
the mind the perspective of someone who
you know genuinely just values
compassion
and by doing that you are
sort of practicing to be compassionate
in everyday life
and uh so
i was that was just sort of in my head
and then um yeah i was also trying to
wrap my head around meta properly
because it just seemed like my idea of
cultivating
compassion but then john's talking about
much suchness and moreness which didn't
make too much sense and then i had the
problem of faith versus remembrance
and then when it was said that reverence
is a forgotten
virtue it just sort of clicked that
maybe
and then i obviously have here the
description of it
it just seemed to sound a lot like what
people were supposed to be doing
that's helpful oh it's so so it was
listening to the woodruff podcast that
you made that connection
yes i think i think that was mainly what
did it oh
what part of it why'd you do that
i'm afraid i don't have a good enough
memory for details to tell you
i just remember that's a big big one
but yeah like the matter that john has
described so far i'm now
episode 50 of the meditation series
that what he seems to have described is
basically
what i said about like you're taking a
virtue and you're putting yourself in
the mind of
the one who has the virtue and it sounds
like that's sort of what you're doing in
metal or you're trying to put yourself
in the mind of the person who is
reverent
i had a slightly different take on meta
if i could share that
i are you still picking me up sorry
yeah oh good so my
recollection of it if you've only done
it recently then
you're closer to the event than i am to
be honest but my
experience with meta was you're
projecting
from within yourself toward
initially others and then expanding i
think somewhat like
mark said previously expanding that
out more broadly so my experience of it
was just thinking about my son
for example and looking at what's
specifically special about him
then looking more broadly what's amazing
about him just as a
creature you know as a human moving on
to my wife
moving on to other family members etc
etc
my experience wasn't necessarily
what would you say mind
as such more
witnessing them without getting too
over the top about it
sorry what what thing then sorry i
didn't hear the verb
my felt experience of it was that i was
witnessing them
yeah i like i like that witnessing i i
think that's good i don't know velascan
where you're getting the entering the
mind of somebody with reverence i don't
i don't even know if that's like
somebody can model reverence for you
right and you can accept and reject it
but i'm not sure how you would
do it imaginely
it sounds like deity yoga or hedon
meditation to me
most correctly
so in in buddhist tantra he might
visualize a bodhisattva
and arise as that bodhisattva uh
imaginably right um and that would be
putting yourself
in the perspective of an enlightened
being
that's the uh the most
direct correspondent of that that i'm
aware of
i'll send you a piece on that just to
clarify
yeah i like you invoke tantra there
that's definitely where i was going in
tantra you would definitely do that
right this is that
idea that i have that the eastern
spiritual physicians are half theist
because sometimes you're supposed to
embody
or or or interact with
uh something like a deity right even
though if you see them in the road
you're supposed to run them over you're
still supposed to have that idea that
that sometimes you're supposed to mirror
that right that's supposed to be your
ideal
sometimes it's just not you're not
supposed to follow that ideal
exclusively and that's what it makes it
sort of half theist
so yeah in tantra i definitely see that
i don't see that so much in john's stuff
because again i think he's going for
i think the two things he's going for
most
by you know in the modifications he's
making will say to the to to to what i
understand the traditions to be and
that's a poor understanding
is is he's trying to engender something
that he thinks might be reciprocal
opening and i think he's right about
that
and and he's also trying to engender
opponent processing
right prajna is all opponent processing
so when he makes modifications
those are the two types of things i
think he's modifying
the current traditions to sort of
engender we'll say i i think that's
that's true but there's definitely sort
of that idea of embodiment
in the eastern spiritual traditions it's
also you know uh
uh possible but but i don't think john
after those
in particular although maybe he should
be maybe we can expand the ecology that
way
i could imagine though that there's a
a functional way in which like even if
you're not
uh overtly setting out to
take on the mind of a reverent person
it's still possible that like
by the end of the practice that is what
you've ended up doing
if that makes sense but i'm not that
experienced with matter
well it could end up happening to you
right that's back to the cultivation
like i like the cultivation right so
in meditation you're cultivating the
field for a bunch of second order
effects or something i think that's an
interesting
way to frame it that might be uh
really useful and then the question
would be why do so many people that
meditate not get
what they want out of it or anything
useful or you know there's a bunch of
ways we could slice that
right they still have uh the the uh
the profound event and they still don't
integrate
mark you should know that the
traditional way to talk about
meta practice is with the phrase uh meta
bhavana
and bhavana one of the meanings of that
word is uh it's translated as
cultivation
as in growing a crop or something so
it is certainly a connection which is
there
and i guess we can kind of see this
happening in joel's vessels
veloskin's experience of
uh witnessing uh versus at least
theoretically
taking uh entering into the mind of
as as just like two possible things that
can spring up within this
cultivation process
i think a connection you can make to
witnessing is
is the suchness right it's
recognizing the specifics without
impeding yourself between
those those your observation and the
interpretation
and then the the opposite thing
would be like projecting that person
into the future right
seeing the potential and then that
that would be the mourners done right
and
and then the mourners your understanding
of the monas
can inform
your observation the suchness and that's
that's the
cycle
yeah manuel i like that that sort of
points to the reciprocal opening
sort of uh mechanism that john's trying
to
create or whatever or uh engender i
guess
so i didn't know that about cultivation
ben thank you for that yeah
i mean i kind of figured it was in there
but all the words and the translations
and
you know it it it takes uh somebody who
studies
uh that sort of stuff uh really well
like yourself to go through that i never
had the patience
um so so i mean that's good like like
we're seeing the same things
so that's that's really interesting and
i i like what you said emanuel about the
the the suchness is the witnessing
right i think that's deeply true right
and then the moreness is something like
the opening
right the the possibility the uh
confrontation with potential
right the unstuckness in time i think
all that tied up in the in the mornings
that's that's also brought to mind the
whole
walking like the the walking with one
foot being meditation
looking at the suchness and the other
foot being
looking through the mornings
like the you're sort of replicating that
yeah john talks a lot about the
ecology's stacking
layering and overlapping those are his
three big things when he talks about
ecologies and what makes good ecology
oh and linking yeah that was the other
one there's a linking in there too yeah
he talks a lot about that when
he's talking about the ecology so um i
don't know how well that comes out in
the series but when i've talked to him
directly about ecologies those are the
words he
he emphasizes the most when we had our
ecology's discussion we'll say
yeah i've heard him say it quite a few
times
what's the difference between stacking
and layering in that description
yeah i'm i'm not really sure how how
john's making the
specific distinction but i i think it's
something like
higher order practices versus
that that fit on top of right or fit
below
uh versus uh an overlap right
and and you know sort of laying two
things
into one another but that are at the
same level we'll say
of interaction or function or something
yeah i like that that's those are the
images that come to mind
one is like you're building a tower and
you need the lower levels before it
works
and the other is you have these two
parts these two lenses one
filters red one filters blue you stack
them over the top of each other and see
what you're left with
i really should have recorded this
i am you are
brilliant
although it's a wonder how much of it
will actually come through given how
many
broken conversations are that it seems
like everybody's having
issues yes it's very frustrating
you guys hear me yeah
so i wanted to take a slightly different
tack
on your initial proposition
uh which is the word reverence
no this might be more manuel's game so
jump in manuel please but
i'm trying to think of the root word
there and
i'm wondering if verity or veritas has
something to do with the center of that
something to do with truth
what does ask about this um
yeah i love my etymologies it's uh
i know it has not got anything to do
with truth
okay very stand in all
your respects ah thanks
so like reverie okay yeah i get it
okay red hearing
yeah it's got something it's got sort of
similar roots to
respect like that means to look back
um
and the the vera is just sort of pay
attention to
instead of just look so
it's very perspectival language
is it not quite sure see
yeah maybe
well there's there's definitely an
element
where there's a negation or or
de-significant of the self
there that that is probably the main
part of right like you're being put into
contrast to something else right where
something else is determining you as
opposed to the other way around
yeah because i guess i think of it as a
at least at the moment the idea of
ourselves is more of a suchness thing
it's what we are
so i'm noticing we're coming up towards
the end of our scheduled times
i'm wondering if the people who are
working on various projects
would like to update the group about
them or not
yeah i asked people at the beginning if
they want to tune in there oh yeah
you don't get anything but yeah if if
anyone didn't hear that please
and i don't have a an official project
but have something to share which is
related okay
okay um a few of you i think
in the room here we're interacting with
a
chap from britain who um
is a quaker there was a very interesting
discussion
generating around it and i just sort of
dropped in on it
and uh had been speaking the previous
day with
my manuel and mark about quakers and
thought oh that's really interesting and
also thinking to myself
how could i serve into the community a
little bit so
i've um arranged with this chap
simon is his name to have a dear logos
about quakerism and uh
how from his perspective i thought it'd
be helpful for a lot of people
can can you all hear me by the way yeah
i thought it'd be helpful because it's
it's an attractive kind of community
but sort of mysterious to many people
including myself
so i thought yeah i'm going to arrange a
deal logos
with him so trying to set it up for
next week maybe next thursday
which would be 8 a.m uk time
unfortunately there's no way for me to
talk to the uk
it's going to be happy for the north
americans
unfortunately so i don't know
how many people are going to jump on or
not jump on
either way i just wanted to show that
everyone hope that it's going to be
useful
my position is going to be trying to
relate as a christian as well how do we
make sense of uh john's teaching like
you know and frankly since he's betting
on ritna
as the way forward why don't we take
that seriously
what does that look like seriously
so i'll put that in the announcement as
uh manuel suggested
probably in the next couple of days
thanks
thank you for putting it on
thanks jb
so yeah like maybe
focus on getting a little bit of
structure going so
maybe get everybody up to date on
what's still happening where we intend
to be going
and that kind of stuff yeah
i'll have to think that through
i guess the projects have sort of
mainly fallen a bit flat at this point
i'm still doing my like i i've shelved
the
perennial problems thing
i had a sort of sense of the very broad
broader definition of perennial problems
that john uses that includes it but goes
beyond it to things sort of like oh well
we all need to deal with death
and interpersonal conflict and so on
um
now i'm on uh practices ecology is like
the whole practices thing because i feel
like it's more
important
so yeah we should maybe just have a
session where we
literally just talk about what kinds of
projects we could
take on although to be honest
usually we go on for another about 40
minutes from here so we could do it
now unless there's some problem with
that
take the wheel
okay then um
so we've got the written our project
so far the projects we've come up with
are the perennial problems
again broader than john perennial needs
which were a more
positive thing which shivarani took on
um we had strewn on analysis of
religions but i don't think that
has really gone anywhere just yet
uh manus i don't know if he's
no he's not here he was doing like this
thing of
motivations values which i prefer to
call
temperaments and andrew l
alternative narrative construction i'm
not sure
that's about exactly oh
yeah like seeing dialogues as a kind of
narrative which is
strewn's idea so
yeah people can go ahead and field some
ideas of
what other projects to have
for my parts i would say that the
analysis religions i think was more
marx's idea than
um and that yeah
he was disputing some of my claims
um the other project
uh with respect to dear lordless
narrative i guess i'm sort of working on
the background anyway
but it's an ongoing
do we have the um problem defined
sufficiently that we can start
working on the problem itself oh yes
that's that's a good point like all
of these projects we we sort of
we came to conclusion on the first
retinal meeting
that we want to focus on problem
definition
so we're not focusing so much on you
know answers about what written is going
to be like
we're focusing more on what problems
we're going to be
trying to trying to solve with retina
well i think that ties into the um
question that i
posed to you the other day
that i think this is actually a good
time
because if we at the video series that
uh john has started with uh craig
enriquez
um where they are talking about the hard
problem of conscious
and i think it's a good question to ask
is exactly
uh what is the hard problem of
consciousness supposed to solve with
respect to the meaning christ
like why is this particular problem
being included in the problem
formulation
should it be there in the first place
anyway so yeah i don't expect anybody to
have answers to that question at the top
of it but i think it's something that i
would like to see
being around but in a written our
discussion context that's a good idea
because yeah it's not entirely clear to
me why it's
relevant at all to be honest
yeah yeah the thing that comes
just going to say wraps off that one
strewn although he's promised
sorry say again oh i said uh
john has not taken the wraps on the link
between
he doesn't take the raps off link
the hard problem being quote unquote
untangled
and spirituality slash meaning crisis
i think that's coming in this week and
the week following
judging by the kind of promissory
comments he's made
sorry did you say the wraps off
taking the wraps off like he hasn't
revealed it he's only kind of promised
it
oh yeah okay oh that's like gloves off i
assume
yeah i'm not i wasn't familiar with the
term or the the
the turner phrase i don't know if that's
uh
australian vernacular or not but um sort
of like you're holding something out but
you've got it
you've got you've got the wrapping on it
yeah yeah yeah
he look it just might say people work
because i think he's
a juicing as usual right
yeah it'd be interesting to see what he
is going to reveal
though i do i i kind of think
part of it's already been laid out in
the the histo
historical factors of the meaning crisis
like i think the hard problem of
consciousness
is very much trying to resolve the
decartean
uh cartesian paradox of um
you know are we enlightened or are we
romantic and
if we can come up with a sami
enlightenment model
that really does justice to
consciousness then
that's addressing a historical factor at
the very least
so what you're suggesting is that the
cartesian
dualism and the
the heart problem of consciousness that
that causes
by when two people who operate on it
at least from an enlightenment
perspective
they're the ones who have a problem so
with respect to the meaning crisis
it's only a meaning crisis problem if
you are
trying to argue for enlightenment not
romanticism to understand you correctly
um
argue from enlightenment um
but i feel like there was criticism of
romanticism as well
yeah yeah no but i'm saying like like so
so to to
to rephrase what i'm saying is um
because the question initially was is
like
what does the heart what does solving
the heart problem of consciousness do if
you
and then you gave me your answer and so
i'm rephrasing what you said
and i'm saying um so what you're saying
is
that like solving the hard problem of
consciousness is useful if you're trying
to argue for an enlightenment kind of
uh position as opposed to a romantic
position
a romantic won't care about the
distinction between like
the heart solving the hard problem of
consciousness is kind of useless to him
like would that be would that be a valid
inference to draw from what you're
trying to say
maybe yeah i mean like i feel like
there's a middle ground
between the two where we still have
souls but we can make logical sense of
the world
and i guess the hard problem of
consciousness in that framing that
you're putting is
trying to reach that middle ground from
the enlightenment side
that's it's one of the angles on this
minion crisis okay
yeah that's that's certainly a a
plausible answer
uh that's that's just what jumps out i'm
super interested to hear what continues
to be revealed or
like what other inputs people might come
up with on their own
yeah i think there was somebody else who
wanted to say something it was like lots
of people talking at the same time there
like a few minutes ago though
well i was gonna say that i i don't
really see the value of solving it
unless the solution is so complicated
that it's inaccessible for most people
or something
right it's like
uh well it might might help with
constructing like the ecology for
example right like if
if there's some profound insight in
how we make connections or something
that
that we can more efficiently make
the connections with that knowledge
yeah i don't i don't see any spiritual
value in in it i don't know
go for it
are you gonna say drills
got some australian internet going on
hey guys can you hear me yes
i've noticed what's happening is uh not
your fault jarvis
but i've noticed every time your tile
lights up
i get booted out so i'll keep an eye on
it
i um i could um
not your fault like i said i could you
still hear me guys
yeah i'm not over my laughter
yeah i'm i'm sorry it's incredibly
frustrating um
but i could take a stab at the
connection that john's trying to go for
using some of his words
as to what the value might be so
the speculation i'd make is
he's saying it connects ultimately to
our capacity to do
relevance realization so how does that
tie into spirituality i'm guessing the
way that it does
is that he's going to replace you still
hear me
man well yeah yep
so he's going to replace consciousness
outside of the split from descartes
onwards he's going to replace it with
fixing the nature problem
he's going to fix the
function problem by casting it in the
light of
function of consciousness comes through
relevance realization
what does it generate it generates
that's the nature problem
uh and i'm very happy for people to take
me to task here it's highly speculative
but what does it generate it generates
real relevance realization and
uh religio religio is how we express
spirituality and so all we need to do
is jump from the dualistic mind body
problem
smash it all together by adopting
relevance realization model of
consciousness
something like that
i'm still coming across
yeah what came through
what do you think's drew and i know
you're yeah go ahead sorry mama
well i was just gonna say that's not a
statement you can easily reply
to right oh yeah that's okay
the difference between kind of stunned
silence and this thing is bloody kicking
me off again i can't tell
yeah i know i sorry i kind of got
distracted by dog jumping on my lap so i
didn't catch all of that i apologize
oh that's cool
sorry stuart and i am actually very
interested in your opinion
short story is my speculation is that
don will
smash the problems which fall out of
dualism which are the function problem
and the nature problem
by bringing it back to the function
of consciousness is relevance
realization the generation
of consciousness is primordially
religio religio is the necessary
outworking of our spirituality we can't
avoid it
therefore uh adopt relevance realization
as the
model for consciousness that that's what
i'm
guessing he's going to go for just just
before spirituality what did you say
i i think before that i said uh that
he's going to talk about the nature
problem and the
function problem and so and then you
said the question probably and you said
the nature but i didn't quite catch that
part so can you repeat that for me
he he coordinates the word
nature problem with generation problem
so
he's interchanging those two so he's
sort of indicating
generation and religion well
to answer the question uh first of all i
am going to propose that what he does is
he's going to say that
the function of consciousness is to do
relevance realization the
thing which consciousness generates is
religio
and religio is because it's necessary to
being a cognitive agent
you can't avoid it it is the house
if you will for our spirituality
did that well so if i understand you
correctly you're kind of saying that the
consciousness generates religion like
that that's
structurally how it's
yeah yeah i think i'd say
yeah yeah i mean did you say that
i can enter i don't know if aveki will
go down that path um
it's an interesting idea uh
i don't know but i mean it's it's not
it's not nonsense
you know it's it's
let's invert it
how would you invert it then well
the the act of social behavior and
and having a dynamical relationship
will generate consciousness right like
no well it depends i don't think viveke
would say that
like it sounds to me like you know
that's why i'm saying
yeah i don't know like the but just
religious ideas
that's what we're thinking about
especially well the question would be is
like how
is it it implies that that
there's something about the structure of
consciousness and connectedness
but there is a some kind of identity
relationship between them
in a deep sense you say that last part
again screw in please
uh there's like a kind of a sort of an
identity relationship between
consciousness and connectedness because
religion
is like the it's the the ligaments that
bind right
so the ligaments that blinded like the
joinings
and so like consciousness what you're
saying is that
the degeneration of consciousness its
fundamental structure
is um is this joining
yes that's very good when i've thought
about
pan psychicism i've thought that it
would have to be
in the interactions where the
consciousness is happening
like the interactions of matter rather
than the matter
necessarily so the relations in other
words yeah exactly
yeah yeah that's spot on the last kind
is drawing please go ahead yeah no
i was just gonna
say that the bindings and the
connections and the
the relatedness i mean those are kind of
obvious
thoughts at least conceptually
so
i'm i'm gonna like blast this open so
i think right like what your
brain does is is necessarily imitation
not relation but
um
sorry um with
with the imitation
it it is
using an existing structure right so
there's
there's also a historical component
that's limiting the imitation
and and in a sense what you get
necessarily is is
is a reduced model
of what is outside
um and that's necessary dynamic because
it always gets updated
like at least that's where my thought is
going about
what what consciousness is right like so
the consciousness is
maybe another world projected by this
world or something
what my thinking is that so so what i
was
sort of getting at is that consciousness
seems to happen
when your neurons are interacting with
each other
so they're having a relationship with
each other so all your thoughts are
aren't just any particular neuron doing
something it's
neurons it's the relationships that are
happening between the firing of
certain neurons and also
um the sorry just one more thing it's uh
i would say that imitation
is gonna have some thing
in there about relating to the
world
but godzilla okay so it sounds
like um regardless of what the content
of
john's discussion about consciousness is
that the problem of consciousness is in
fact relevant to retina
so we're we're basically all going on
okay so with
conscious i think consciousness is this
i think consciousness is this but
basically what it's coming down to
is um that uh yes um
the problem of consciousness is relevant
to what we're discussing
um no no but
i i that that's the question like it
could just be a
uh a rabbit hole that we go that we've
all gone down that actually serves no
purpose
and that actually the solution or the
problem we're facing is something
completely unrelated to the hard problem
of consciousness
all right in that case i'll point out
that um consciousness
is how we experience the world and so
um if um how we experience the world
and why we experience the world is going
to affect
um how what we feel is meaningful
therefore learning but we don't need a
theory of consciousness for that
that that's okay but if you it but
learning about why you have
consciousness and
how you have consciousness will affect
um what you feel is meaningful
um so that's uh like
um consciousness is how you experience
the world
if you if you um meditate and you're
experiencing the world differently
then that affects how you see things and
that's going to affect
um your sense of meaning yes
right but that's already true without
knowing what consciousness is
yeah there's there's no it's not obvious
why you have to
say any of that and the hard problems
conscious together
like that could be completely unrelated
it could be completely unrelated but um
if we have a if we can get a better idea
a better grasp of
how and why we experience consciousness
that's going to
affect the problem formulation and it's
going to affect the solutions that are
available to us
yes but okay so there is the problem of
the hard problem of consciousness right
so there's a problem i don't know how
much effort we actually have to expand
and what it will take to get the
solution
because so well it's a high problem so
uh maybe there will never be a solution
to that problem
yeah but any information we have towards
that is going to be
um useful no because
it doesn't have to be useful right like
this is this is the problem with
information right like
if if you relate to the world
the useful things are the things that
optimize your relationship to the world
and
like me and mark were talking about
post-modernism for example and nihilism
they're like like black holes right like
they're like pits that just suck you in
and and they're not productive right so
engaging with those ideas is just
not gonna resolve anything it's not
going to bring
any fruit right it's it's not going to
sow
any fields it's just going to suck
energy
so it's it it is not clear to me that
dealing with consciousness is is
fruitful
in in a pragmatic sense
you're dealing with consciousness now
the way you experience the world is
through consciousness
yes but i i have ways of dealing with
consciousness without knowing the true
nature of it
it's like you you don't actually need to
know how your car works to use your car
like you don't learn how cars well yes
but if you know how your car
works then you can solve problems
related to
your car better we are talking about um
demeaning crisis which is
a problem that the consciousness has
with a lot with a lack of meaning
right right okay so i think head doesn't
care that there's no meaning
right but i think i can make the
metaphor meaningful here by saying
um it's not clear that knowing exactly
how the car works is going to tell you
where you want to go
like that that it's not obvious at least
if if that is the claim that you want to
make or that anyone wants to make
i think an argument needs to be made in
favor of you can't just assume that that
is the case that
once you know how the car works you're
going to know where you want to go
i'm not arguing that you all know i'm
arguing
that this is information that affects
how you think about things
and if you and um the meaning crisis is
a problem with how you think about
things
right but more information is not always
better
like this is relevance realization
right it could be like you could be at
the tech
i'm not saying let's do some research
i'm saying let's listen to the research
that johns of 80
is doing and is making videos about
yeah that's not dealing with the point
right like when
when your your conception of self
gets more complex you have more
variables to relate to
that means your
your road is going to be more difficult
because you're you're going to
have to deal with okay but on the other
hand you're not dealing with an overly
simplified version of self
if the self is too it is too complex
then you can't solve the problem
if the thought the self is too
simplified then the problem is
meaningless
it seems like there's an equivocation
that's
confusing this conversation
between like
[Music]
like having a fact known by a field
versus
um like actively
uh applying a fact in your life
when john and greg try to solve the hard
problem of consciousness
they're not trying to make you study the
hard problem of consciousness they're
just trying to
solve it to see to see what does come
out of that
and i think like the field
exploring things adjacent to the meaning
crisis
um is definitely a different
program to the program of like
working out what individuals should do
within the meaning crisis but
um there's a higher order relation
between those two
helps resolve this conflict
so my takeaway from the two videos with
between john and greg was not that
they're trying
the value doesn't come from actually
solving the problem
of consciousness but from reframing
how we think about problem of
consciousness
and for most people it's going to be the
reframing
of the problem that actually brings
value to their lives
and i think i agree with people who say
who say just having
the information more information isn't
necessarily going to help
although i also agree that the
information will have an effect
but i think the important part
for actually where retinal fits in
is that i think retina is going to have
to
provide a reframing of the problem
of of the seeming duality between
consciousness and physical material
whether reality not it actually solves
it yes it sort of occurred to me that uh
it might be part of how
re-homing us in the world maybe
where it might be part of a narrative
maybe
at some time but
yeah i'd say it's also uh the process um
metaphor or relation giving rise to
consciousness
is analogous to transactivity being more
fundamental
than the the schizophrenic split between
subjectivity and
objectivity that john often talks about
and that could fit into the narrative as
well
and i think he's also trying to break
down the simple dichotomy with
uh the help of greg having like the four
or three or four different kinds of mind
like the self-conscious phenomenology
and then the self-justification system
in order to problematize
the idea of just consciousness being one
thing
uh when you say consciousness just being
one thing can you elaborate slightly
what you mean by that idea
yeah so i feel like most people have the
idea that it's
um i presumably from from descartes
where it's their uh
sense of ability to think and direct
their attention or some kind of
combination of all those things whereas
greg's model uh differentiated between
the
um i can pose a picture but he had a
nice picture of the the lower
left section of the internal state of
like a different loops of
information process thing and then one
higher which was
uh a recursive sense of uh
phenomenal self and then
yeah so you basically mean the idea that
the mind is complex
not simple
the the lower one that i just mentioned
like component processing no no i mean
in general like the idea is that the
mind is simple
not complex it's like if your mind is
complex and there's many parts working
together if it's simple then that
aren't really any part just the whole
like people
the simple view of consciousness is that
it's just this kind of self-contained
hole
yeah and i think that that's related to
john's critiques of like the simple
ideas of
of pansexism as well versus deep
continuity
um but i don't think they're trying to
solve the hard problem at least
from what they've said but try to like
circle it and make it smaller
as far as i understood
well fair enough
but yeah i liked the idea of religio
giving rise to consciousness rather than
vice versa since that would kind of
relate to the idea of transactivity
being the locus of meaning
and maybe consciousness being like the
ground of meaning in the first place
rather than the cartesian dualism having
the
the relation between things uh huffman's
idea
um like uh well that reality is an
illusion
um that that matter is
is is a derivative of consciousness
in some sense it's like uh how does he
put it
the the matter is is basically something
that your your consciousness interface
generates in order to be able to
interact with the world
like so the consciousness is logically
prior to the matter
yeah i mean there's like the less
radical interpretation of that which is
basically
cons that everything is filtered through
our evolutionarily
derived senses but then there's also
maybe the more
extreme version of that which is
something like uh whitehead's idea that
uh process or the field is more
fundamental than the particles
themselves which is i assume what
hoffman's getting at kind of
um no i mean
um hoffman's actually quite
but what i understand it's like he uh
hoffman has his own way of talking about
the
the process and the the and the
substance
um like he has them both he's not he's
not trying to to shift off of the
the substance into process he's um
well he's he i don't know he's kind of
speculative in the way that he thinks
right
he's kind of like well yeah my ideas are
very daring but they specific and they
testable and that's good science yada
yada yada right so he
he he knows that he's making provocative
statements right
so but from what i understand is like
his idea of
like he's literally trying to reverse
the idea of of
um because most people physicalist or
whatever they think okay you've got
physics and then physics somehow gives
rise to conscious
he inverts that he says okay you've got
consciousness and then it somehow gives
rise to physic
like he's he's explicitly trying to make
that argument and
well i mean he might be wrong but but
it's a very interesting way of looking
so i mean i really like often
like yeah i just definitely noticed
that yeah i mean i i enjoyed them as
well but like
um yeah well hoffman is just
yeah i don't know there's something
really elegant about the way he thinks
yeah i agree
but i'm not too yeah i know greg greg
and john also well i don't know greg
that well yet i like quite a couple
other things
john i like his dis like
this strikes me as a really disappointed
more like that that's his most
exceptional
feature i would say in terms of his
thinking the discipline
and you know i kind of learned
yeah i learned about why i think i
learned the value of that
like at least the value of trying to
emulate
yeah i'd say humility as well in my
experience
that's a dirty word
[Laughter]
that might be an interesting discussion
uh weren't we kind of connecting
humility to reverence earlier
yeah i don't know like
i mean i i can i don't know i think it's
a
there's an equivocation going on because
like you've got
there's humility versus pride and
humility versus hubris almost right
and like humility pride is
always well not always but it's often
seen as
bad no matter what right but there's
there's such a thing as taking pride in
your work
and so there's like a i don't know but
like
maybe that's the misuse of the word
pride
no i don't think so because i think it's
such a thing as taking
pride in your work and being proud of
who you are and and being willing to
stand up for yourself
and like you can't you can't just think
that you're like
the biggest in life and there's
something
there comes a point where humility is no
longer honest
and like no you know if if you are the
best in the world it's something like
you should be proud
like you did something that that is that
is
noteworthy like you're better than
everybody else even if it's only one
thing that like there's a million
other things with people better other
than you acting right the one thing that
you did that that's significant
it should be recognized and you should
be able to say if it's honest if
if you actually have the the these
results to back it up it's like well i'm
the best in the world
so i i think i've resolved this issue
so there's a distinction between
an act of will and an act of
agency right and then in in some
sense you you're not responsible for
your capacity
right like the the capacities
are just there they're available to you
so
taking pride in that or whatever i think
is wrong
right but when when
when you're you're struggling right and
and you're you're you're having an act
of will
right like maybe taking pride in that
but i
i don't know if i want to use the word
pride there but
but at least respect for for that
is is important i also like
to i like to define the
i like i like having two words
no i've noticed that we often use two
words for the same
virtue if you're thinking about it in
aristotelian terms so humility is the
virtue
relative to hubris or arrogance
but obviously there's the other pole of
basically hating yourself and so
relative to that you might say
confidence
so like i understand self-respect yeah
something like that
well to to speak to manuel's example
first of all i don't
buy the distinction between will and
agents i mean that like what are you
even talking about but aside from that
um it's like okay you are born with
let's say the best abilities in the
world you say it's wrong to take pride
in it it's like
well if you don't take pride in it will
you actually make the best and
my answer would be no it's like the
pride is the price you have to pay
in order to to bring it out the best
that is possible
of that talent or that natural ability
whatever you're making like
50 assumptions there that i all disagree
with probably
why why would you have to make the best
of that skill
like that's not a given at all no
but if you don't then you're not taking
advantage of whatever the natural
capability is
so if
no i don't think we're talking about the
same thing
i think one of the distinctions i would
make between pride and arrogance for
example would be
uh you can take pride in your own skill
but
acknowledging the other factors that
weren't
under your control that went into uh
your
capability to have that skill in the
first place even if one of those
is genes for example like john often
citing other researchers that he's
collaborated with that
you know or people that you've stood on
the shoulders of that have written
previous topics before you without
self-effacing your accomplishment
i think it yeah i think it's as simple
as you can't just
call it a virtue to recognize your
limits
you also need to recognize your power
your
capacities
yeah well here's a practical example as
if you become a heart surgeon
you're the best you know like taking
pride in your abilities of the heart
surgeon like your manual dexterity
even if it's a natural-born talent the
the taking the pride in it is what's
going to make you practice
is what's going to make you actually
want to be the best is going to want to
make you put in the effort to be the
best
like if you don't take pride in it you
wouldn't do that so
you don't necessarily want everybody to
think you want to try to become a heart
surgeon
but insofar as there is such a thing as
a good heart surgeon
you the the best heart surgeons will be
the ones who take pride in heart surgery
in their heart or their their capacity
for heart surgery
those that don't probably will neglect
their art in some respect because they
don't take it serious
that's my point
and as i'm saying like i mean obviously
somebody can go and like you know i'm
the best heart surgeon therefore you
know you should kiss my my shoe
my shoes every morning when i wake up
you know that that would obviously be
taking something too far that's not
that's not quite what i'm talking
yeah i agree it's one factor that would
push people um
to like get to the the top of their
of their capacities although i wonder
whether uh
it's possible for someone to have the
like the locus of
itself that that john talks about um
like getting rid of the
like the self the self-conscious
snattering nanny or whatever
in the flow states um but you'd still
have pride after
after the fact i guess is what you're
saying to want to push you to
to get into that state again even better
in your craft
yeah well i mean i i could i could
certainly see how somebody
uh who had a natural ability for
something became narcissistic and
because of their narcissism
you know they they're sitting there in
the operating table and they think oh
i'm such a great heart surgeon you know
look at me
and you know they're busy like
perforating the guy's hearts in their
different places
because they aren't doing i could see
that as well
so i i think my objection to
what you're trying to do strong is that
there's a whole set of other virtues who
can also be used to explain that
behavior and
contextualize it and i don't see why
you would focus on pride as a primary
way of
analyzing that situation
well that's just the word that comes to
mind
yeah like i think it's one of the
possible motivations but they may also
do it because they had you know someone
else that they
loved that died from having a poor
surgery and they wanted to
kind of make up make it up to that
person so it's not as
as you go like as maybe another person
would
um but i'm guessing you'd think that the
more motivation
types maybe the the more likely they
would be to be at the best of their
skill yeah well i mean
i if the only reason that people want to
become heart surgeons like
yeah i don't know i mean it's all well
and good for somebody to have a
family member who died tragically and
then you know for that to serve as the
inspiration for somebody to
to never have somebody else suffer ever
again but um
i don't know if people are actually
wired that way i don't know if that's
true of the average
right but now
we're in the realm of well necessary
evil as opposed to
goodness right like
okay well i'm happy to argue that pride
might be necessary
it seems also like uh there might be
a having mode thing here where
like you're trying to describe a
thing that might be called pride that is
legitimate in the having mode
of like
uh reduce the number of people with
heart problems
and in order to do that i need to become
superior
in my ability to like
whereas like this humility discussion is
trying to solve a problem
in the being mode and from that
perspective i feel like you'd want you'd
want both you just want them in their
proper place
but
i'm sorry i obviously take no pride in
my ability to pay attention because i
was laughing too much at the fact that
you'll
continue bouncing out of the channel
you're talking
and i wanted to say something to you can
i say it now
yeah yeah so i've thought about this
uh tension myself quite a bit and i
think you'd find it
um helpful to do
the dialogue between aristotle and
aquinas
on this very subject so
in aristotle he pays no
no mind to humility and i think the
greeks in general
didn't value it as a virtue it's
probably
the exception that they were always on
the lookout for hubris
that being said aquinas
did his summer theologica and he went
through it
as rigorously as you could possibly go
and he kind of tempered
so what you have in aristotle's virtues
is magnaminity
which i think literally translates as
big solidness
he or she who has a big soul and i think
it's
roughly translated to if you look into
what he's saying he's saying it is good
to be proud of your abilities and who
you are
in fact that's a virtue and that didn't
strike christians
well it struck it as a conflict which
needed resolution
and that's what aquinas set himself
toward
in the sumer i can't
remember i'm sorry how he resolved it
but i think it was like basically
something like the virtue of humility
stops you from having
the wrong impression of
your abilities in other words it allows
you to have the accurate
assessment of what you are and what you
can achieve
well i i think there is such a thing
as understanding a limitation
right i don't think i don't think i
wouldn't i wouldn't i wouldn't
want to endorse a sense of pride
was not understanding
that last part i say i wouldn't want to
endorse a sense of pride that it wasn't
um
that it wasn't mindful of your
limitations yeah right
because that wouldn't be skillful would
it going to your doctor
exactly like you wouldn't like that
that's not yeah
that's not the pride that gets you to be
the best at what you are it's not that's
all right
it's not what you mean by when you when
you try and take you know like if you
take pride in your work
it's not like that taking
pride isn't is is also an awareness of
your limitations
yeah it really does like i really really
do feel
like probably the way that strewn's
saying the word pride i would prefer
confidence but
you know the way you're using the word
yeah the way you're using the word pride
is literally the virtue relative to
the deficiency and humility is the
virtue relative
to the excess but they're the same thing
it's it's about getting the right
view of yourself and that involves
knowing your limitations
and knowing your capabilities
i'd put that under justice actually
but that's can't wait i'm sorry
well justice is having having the things
be as they should right
as in not too much not too little
well yeah but also that things come to
expression
in the way they're supposed to come into
right like
that that's the engine between your
actual age heritage their manual
well yeah that that's that's what i'm
hearing when you say pride is like
well do things as they're supposed to be
right like and then
no i mean i think that they
yeah i mean at least historically that
was i think there's a lot of legitimacy
to that that's how justice was seen
at least in the good old you know the
like the ancient days not not the
medieval or the one so you know
yeah that sense my actual age robot
are we still recording by the way if you
stopped uh
i can stop anytime so
okay so you're still going
but no this is interesting so may as
well include it
can everybody get all self-conscious at
once now
huh
yeah where's all that pride that you
guys are speaking of like
[Laughter]
yeah you see this is this is i know what
i lack so
so going back to projects um
fully caught up with the written our
world i'm not
like fully participating yet but i think
like one thing
on my mind looking forward is
uh like a retina analog to
and to like art that people participate
in
uh sorry you cut out when you said the
word
oh liturgy liturgical practice
oh yeah yeah and
and uh
i think a lot about video game design
which is kind of
an abysmal uh mode of expression
as it's currently used but um
like that already has a participation
built into it
um but also like you know all of the
existing art forms which um
have a place in religious traditions
uh but have like lost their religious
connection in the modern world
it's something that i think deserves a
lot of humility
and like not
not underestimating the the challenge of
making
spiritually profound art but like i
think that would be a very interesting
like long-term goal of retina
i have actually been thinking about like
that's the main way
i think about uh when i'm uh
just you know just thinking
thoughts for the fun of it i think about
how
video games would be
possibly a superior way of
transmitting a myth because you are
actually
literally participating in it
are you actually involved in the myth if
you made a video game
meant to transmit like a narrative or
myth
so that's interesting so you you're
you're stepping on my project
oops yeah but i i thought your games
were like
uh d and d
which is like imagining you well i
mean like that
haven't foreclosed on anything right and
the idea is to make as many
as possible but yeah the
distinction that i'd like to draw with
the suggestion is that i don't
want to look at them liturgy i want to
look at them
as tools
for self-development
and part of that would be a concept that
we call historical grounding
where you're contextualizing the
experience
of the person within themselves and
their their direct history and their
their more ancient history and and
making that connection
is something like narrative
rising information
in in a way that that
that grounds that person in in at least
in relationship to the game but
uh hopefully in a more permanent way
to do a meaningful thing
yeah well that's awesome i'm super
interested to see where that goes with
both of you
and interested in like what discussions
each of us might
be able to have about these things
because um
they're exciting and very adjacent to
things that i'm interested in
yeah in my last conversation with john i
tried making an argument for the
uh potentially video games as uh
training
in virtue through the combination of the
appreciation for
for beauty along with the flow state
induction they're just often
not used to that potential and i
try to get in contact with daniel greg
who i know is doing the
like some kind of rpg as well doing
serious play
um i don't know if anyone has
familiarity with his project or is in
contact with him but i'm definitely
interested in this because
in the past uh video games i i agree
have
a lot of potential before creating a
sacred space of perspectival and
participatory
um i guess you could say liturgy maybe
it it would be liturgy if you're
playing it together i guess because it's
liturgies uh people coming together for
their spiritual
practice so so the biggest
obstacle i see is that games have a
tendency to
be related to in the having mode right
and that's
yeah even even if you're in a flow state
if you're in flow state
right like like an addiction right like
i want to have the flow state but that's
not
a reverence way of of
engaging right so so that's where i
think
this historical grounding stuff is is
necessary
because that's that's presupposed in
reverence i think
like the fact that you have a way of
contextualizing
your experience and a way of
of relating to it that that is
more than just getting your your fix
yeah you need to have a very
specific way of making sure that it's
connecting to real life
maybe bridging practice don't know
yeah this is something that i study a
lot like for the sake of game design on
its own so
um to import
some of the like game designers
that i know like have things to say
about addictive games versus
um more perspectival
ways of playing uh there's there's a lot
that
if if you guys are considering these
things uh
i'd love to import some of it to make it
more accessible
yeah i'd love to talk more about this
so let's uh run
it up at least for the recording so
everybody
thanks for participating i'll be having
a
new version of this next week
at the same time which is vlaskan
it's 7 p.m est and
midnight bst
uh we're supposed to watch a video for
that
yes and that will be broadcasted on the
discord
so yes thanks
for listening everyone